<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright 2026 Srinivas Gowda -->
<component type="desktop-application">
  <id>io.github.solancer.Sarala</id>

  <name>Sarala</name>
  <summary>Seamless WYSIWYG Markdown editor</summary>

  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>

  <developer id="io.github.solancer">
    <name>Srinivas Gowda</name>
  </developer>

  <description>
    <p>
      Sarala is a fast, distraction-free WYSIWYG Markdown editor with no preview
      pane and no split view — the editing surface is the preview. Every
      paragraph, heading, list, quote, table and code fence is a live block:
      click into one and it opens to raw Markdown, click away and it renders in
      place. One parser, one theme, one window — what you see while writing is
      exactly what exports.
    </p>
    <p>
      Files are read and written as plain Markdown, so your documents are never
      locked into a proprietary format.
    </p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Live block editing — Markdown styles itself as you type, with dimmed syntax markers that render fully on Enter or when the caret moves away</li>
      <li>Smart Enter that continues lists, numbering, task items and blockquotes, and auto-closes code fences</li>
      <li>GitHub Flavored Markdown: tables, task lists, strikethrough, and syntax-highlighted fenced code</li>
      <li>Math with KaTeX (inline and block) and diagrams with Mermaid and D2</li>
      <li>Find and replace, an Open Quickly fuzzy finder, and a command palette</li>
      <li>Sidebar with a file tree and a live document outline</li>
      <li>Source, Focus and Typewriter modes</li>
      <li>Export to HTML and PDF, plus docx, odt, rtf, epub, LaTeX and more via Pandoc</li>
      <li>Built-in themes: Paper, Graphite, GitHub, Night, Newsprint and Whitey</li>
    </ul>
  </description>

  <launchable type="desktop-id">io.github.solancer.Sarala.desktop</launchable>

  <content_rating type="oars-1.1" />

  <url type="homepage">https://github.com/solancer/sarala</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/solancer/sarala/issues</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/solancer/sarala</url>

  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/solancer/sarala/main/docs/screenshot.png</image>
      <caption>Editing a Markdown document with live blocks, an outline sidebar and the theme palette</caption>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>

  <branding>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="light">#f4f1ea</color>
    <color type="primary" scheme_preference="dark">#2b2b2b</color>
  </branding>

  <categories>
    <category>Office</category>
    <category>Utility</category>
  </categories>

  <keywords>
    <keyword>Markdown</keyword>
    <keyword>Editor</keyword>
    <keyword>WYSIWYG</keyword>
    <keyword>Writing</keyword>
    <keyword>Notes</keyword>
  </keywords>

  <releases>
    <release version="0.4.3" date="2026-07-09">
      <description>
        <p>Each Monokai theme variant now has its own distinct signature accent. First release available as a Flatpak on Flathub.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.2" date="2026-07-09">
      <description>
        <p>UI polish: Inter font across all platforms, crisp sidebar hover, a stable Recent Files list and icons in the menu bar dropdowns.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.1" date="2026-07-09">
      <description>
        <p>Linux font parity with macOS and Windows, and an on-launch check that offers to install a newer release when one is available.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.4.0" date="2026-07-08">
      <description>
        <p>Auto-updater and a range of editor refinements.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.3.0" date="2026-07-07">
      <description>
        <p>Diagram support (Mermaid and D2), export presets and additional themes.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.2.0" date="2026-06-17">
      <description>
        <p>Find and replace, Open Quickly fuzzy finder, and the sidebar file tree and outline.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release version="0.1.0" date="2026-06-16">
      <description>
        <p>First public release.</p>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
